[SPEAKER_04]: So, this is some excerpts from a talk by Ajahn Chah called Right View, the Place of Coolness.
Coolness.
[SPEAKER_04]: Just a few paragraphs.
[SPEAKER_04]: The practice of dhamma goes against our habits.
[SPEAKER_04]: The truth goes against our desires.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, there is difficulty in the practice.
[SPEAKER_04]: Some things which we understand as wrong, may be right, while the things we take to be right, may be wrong.
[SPEAKER_04]: Why is this?
[SPEAKER_04]: Because our minds are in darkness.
[SPEAKER_04]: We don't clearly see the truth.
[SPEAKER_04]: We don't really know anything, and so are fooled by people's lies.
[SPEAKER_04]: They point out what is right as being wrong, and we believe it.
[SPEAKER_04]: That which is wrong, they say is right, and we believe that.
[SPEAKER_04]: This is because we are not yet our own masters.
[SPEAKER_04]: Our moods lie to us constantly.
[SPEAKER_04]: We shouldn't take this mind and its opinions as our guide, because it doesn't know the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that, that's the paragraph done?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, like, for example, that's a very good example of how differently you can take what he just said.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, obviously, you can't trust your moods, you don't have a criteria, you don't have a right reference point to know whether you are right and what's right is right and wrong is wrong, as the Buddha would say.
[SPEAKER_00]: But most people that I heard they would be palloting Ajahn Chah, would use this very thing he would say to justify dismissing everything and not committing to anything, because everything is not sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he doesn't say that, clearly.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, yeah, that's your starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't trust things until you become your master and you know right is right and wrong is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, those same people would be saying, oh, nothing is sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You shouldn't trust anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just opinion.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just a view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, at the same time, then develop a view that there is nothing to be attained as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, of course, when you're dismissing everything, there is no goal for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no place that you can sort of achieve through your efforts.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would then go beyond the views and you would be the master of
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, the suttas, that's all they talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you see Ajahn Chah, that's all he talks about.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I like that last sentence.
[SPEAKER_04]: We shouldn't take this mind and its opinions as our guide.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can say that, aha, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I must not hold to any views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Failing to see that that is the view you hold on to.
[SPEAKER_00]: View of I will not commit to any view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you should not commit to any view, so that you can keep looking for the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, not like, I will not commit to any view as a goal in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remember even the chant that's done in the temples in Europe, uh, I will not hold to fixed views.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's a fixed view in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Refusing to hold to fixed views.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even the Buddha said that, the same, when the man said, no view pleases me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he, and the Buddha told him, well, surely that view is pleasing to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: The one that everything is displeasing to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, people think they can just find a way out of views through not committing to any views, and that's a quite a popular belief.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, they would quote people like Ajahn Chah saying... and you see how much misquoting there would be, because he doesn't say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, your starting point is you don't know right is right, wrong is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a pretentious place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to make the effort to clarify, not make the effort and not commit to anything, because everything is risky and dangerous.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I'll continue.
[SPEAKER_04]: Some people don't want to listen to others at all, but this is not the way of a man, a wise man.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, let me add to that as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for example, people might think, oh, no, I have no problem listening to others.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you really want to take that seriously.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's when, when a person, like you ask yourself, if I were to face someone else's view,
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, say, I think this... what practice is, I think it's like this, and you do that, and whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, somebody else comes and challenges that, or not even personally challenges me, but simply has a different view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to ask yourself, would I be affected by that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I threatened?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I feel I need to defend myself on account of opposing views that don't agree with me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do I feel I need to justify myself to myself?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, yeah, I might not get into an argument with that person, but am I personally affected by the opposing view?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does it cause the doubt?
[SPEAKER_00]: Does it make unrest?
[SPEAKER_00]: Me experience unrest or similar?
[SPEAKER_00]: If the answer is yes, that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to hear others.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you're not wise, and that's why you're not developing wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because you don't go and... oh, I'll go and debate with everybody that... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't learn like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You learn by understanding right is right, wrong is wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you keep protecting whatever you got,
[SPEAKER_00]: Out of fear of maybe you're wrong, means you won't know wrong is wrong and right is right, because you're not committing to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's absolutely no reason to be affected by anything, let alone someone else's view, to cause emotion arise in you or anything like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's absolutely no justification for that.
[SPEAKER_04]: A wise man listens to everything.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what does that mean?
[SPEAKER_04]: He listens and contemplates.
[SPEAKER_00]: He listens and he understands what that thing is saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: He understands the meaning of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly how he can know whether it's right or not, whether it's according to the dhamma or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you understand the meaning of something, if you never make the effort to understand it?
[SPEAKER_00]: If your efforts are about not committing to anything, not holding to any views, watching your nostrils, how can you then understand that?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you don't.
[SPEAKER_04]: Even if the teacher speaks the truth, don't just believe it, because you don't yet know the truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And not, oh, you must understand it for yourself, as in, are you going to have a mystical experience for yourself?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you need to understand it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you understand it, you will be able to explain it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will be able to put it in words.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not made it completely inexpressible, idiosyncratic experience that nobody can relate to it, but you know it's my truth.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, that's just a mystical experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the truth of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to understand the universal nature of experience that's in common to all beings that contain five... that are made of five aggregates, which is all beings.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you'll be free.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's why anyone can relate to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the dhamma is the path that doesn't change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether it's revealed or not, it stays the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: The universal principles remain the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it can't be revealed to you if you if you're not making effort to reveal it, to discern it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It just cannot be given, cannot occur accidentally or spontaneously.
[SPEAKER_00]: Suddenly you spontaneously develop wisdom.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because that's quite common to say.
[SPEAKER_04]: I feel, I know that... Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: I know that I know.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can't put it in words, but it was a real thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it was a real thing as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: A real mystical experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you can't put it in words, you haven't understood it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha would say, as far as the language, as far as the designation goes, the Tathāgata has understood it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I'll continue with the Ajahn Chah passage.
[SPEAKER_04]: It says, most of us have wrong view.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's just like a maggot.
[SPEAKER_04]: A maggot lives... his living place is filthy.
[SPEAKER_04]: Its food is filthy.
[SPEAKER_04]: But they suit a maggot.
[SPEAKER_04]: If you take a stick and brush it away from its lump of dung, it struggles to crawl back in.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's the same when the teacher teaches us to see rightly.
[SPEAKER_04]: We resist it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Make us... it makes us feel uneasy.
[SPEAKER_04]: We run back to our lump of dung.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because of that... because that's where we feel at home.
[SPEAKER_04]: We're all like this.
[SPEAKER_04]: If we don't see the harmful consequences of our wrong views, then we can't leave them.
[SPEAKER_04]: Practice is difficult.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, we should listen.
[SPEAKER_04]: There's nothing else to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you should listen.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the one that's talking to you knows what he's talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: You shouldn't just listen somebody appointed a teacher by the institution of tradition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, good luck with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you should listen, but you should also discern who you listen to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, yeah, I mean,
[SPEAKER_00]: You can interpret that bit in the same sense, like, you know, when somebody comes as a layman, become a monk, sense restraint means I'm going against my my will, I'm going against my environment of dhamma that I used to be, that I was used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the Ādhyācārya talks about the views, not just, not just the sense restraint and, and renunciation, but the actual views.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's, that's where the difference is.
[SPEAKER_00]: How many people actually actively challenge their existential views?
[SPEAKER_00]: How many people, like, invite on the existential doubt in order to uproot it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And not many.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many people can live a perfectly restrained life, and that's very nice.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't differentiate you from a restrained householder.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right view does.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for right view, you just being a renunciate, that's not enough.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, how to challenge your views.
[SPEAKER_00]: How to challenge your views, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not like, oh, I'll just do what the teacher says, which is a common practice in Thailand.
[SPEAKER_00]: I won't read the suttas, I won't think for myself, I just do what Ajahn tells me to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if Ajahn is an arahant himself, that's not enough for you to become one.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just do what he tells you to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what it said in the... in the... before we spoke about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't just accept it as it is, even if it's your own teacher.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, there's the other paragraph.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you should listen.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have a good faith, based on your own discernment, that what you are listening to is correct, then, yeah, you should listen and make the effort to do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: It says, if we have right view, wherever we go, we are content.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because wherever you go, you're out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: Or, as Nyanaviru was talking about, the sense of safety.
[SPEAKER_04]: The safety ground.
[SPEAKER_04]: The safe ground.
[SPEAKER_00]: The right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not shorter than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why I keep insisting with people, trying to... trying to justify not having the right view, but... but arguing that they're on the right track of their practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only know that if you have the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, until you have a right view, you shouldn't think you're on the right track, because it will make you complacent to that extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's... that's exactly what Ajahn Chah is saying there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only place of safety and coolness is the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no lower than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you are aiming for lower than that, you can expect to be even lower than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you should really be aiming for higher than that, to at least get the right view then, as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let me finish these quotations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, finish them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can I just come back to that first one, when he said that we should not trust our moods?
[SPEAKER_01]: But, you know, our moods are also like part of our experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not trusting the moods doesn't mean denying them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means not acting out of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to act out of your mood, you must have taken it for granted.
[SPEAKER_03]: Same.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to act out of sensuality, you took it at a face value.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to act out of ill-will, you took it at a face value.
[SPEAKER_00]: You trust it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not trusting it doesn't mean, oh, I'm not accepting this.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means I don't act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means I'm aware of it in its persistence, basically, for what it is, and I'm not trusting it to make me act and do things out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how the another thing that people keep quoting on which everything is teaching us.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how everything teaches you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of your attitude in regard to everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because everything is actually teaching you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which basically again brings that thing that we must put the effort to understand or to practice that the teaching is about the...
[SPEAKER_00]: Nature of things means anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Partakes in that nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you discern in the nature, means anything will be partaking in your discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you say, basically, when you say, like, you don't, if you don't have right view, you don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this can actually put everyone who has no right view in the position of, like, you know, like, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, and then he can, he can be, or that person can be, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, I'm not confident actually to express anything, to do anything, and just trying to follow someone, because you would always say, you know, I don't know, I still don't have right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but following, following someone, that person would be fully aware that I have no right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, following someone on account of me not having a right view, has nothing to do with me not having the right view or having the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, they would not be justified in following someone.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wouldn't make them follow someone.
[SPEAKER_01]: But what I mean is more like, you know, then there can be a person who is just claiming, yes, I have right view, and all these unconfident people who don't have right view, who just go and follow him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but that's because they don't have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, that's exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not what this is saying either.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just quite the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Someone else's right view doesn't do anything for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's even what the first quote said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's your own teacher, as in somebody who doesn't know what he's talking about, you must investigate that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't just follow it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't just take it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the person who is like following the teaching of the Buddha, he has basically right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sotāpaṭṭhāna has the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but you have also this lokīyā right view, this ordinary right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but that's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you are not ārya, so you actually don't...
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a right view, but... No, it's a mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm talking about sotāpaṭṭhāna, freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mundane right view doesn't free you from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's still kind of right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a right basis for the right view of the subject.
[SPEAKER_00]: The right view that matters is the sotāpanna's right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, it doesn't mean that lay right view doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means you can't have sotāpanna's right view without the mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But mundane right view, you're still a putujuna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the sense of safety starts with sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not with putujuna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, mundane right view is not the sense of safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so we are speaking about this ārya right view, not the ordinary... Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... that's what I said there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, we can speak about the mundane right view and you realize most people don't... most monks don't even have it, not even mundane right view, despite being in robes for 40-50 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: You think so?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, most certainly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you start thinking about the mundane right view, you realize it's already quite an accomplishment in undoing lots of wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite a lot of self-transparency developed through mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognition of the nature of things through mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you hear the the other people, monks, whatever, speaking, you realize they don't even have the basic recognition of those views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, please, can you actually speak about this mundane right view, you know?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, we spoke before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remember, I think, I think it was with you that I spoke about the authenticity and self-transparency.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, that's... That's exactly what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognition of the validity of the risen phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is given, there is good, there is bad, there is mother, there is father, there is the fact that I don't know something.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is the next life, there is this life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, all these things is basically a recognition of the state of mind as it is, not coming out of a view that you have preconceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, there is rebirth, because I believe in it, you know, because I see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, there is no rebirth, because I don't believe in it, not because I see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you recognize it, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first bit for me, it's not there is rebirth, there isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is lack of knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a factual thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you recognize it as an arisen thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you know, like, people might say, oh, yeah, there is mother, there is father.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you were to ask them, they would jump on to the view of modern science and medicine and explaining that it's just a bunch of molecules and electrons.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing in reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's real.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything is constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you see that fully committed Buddhist people and practitioner undermine the basic reality of the world that they've experienced themselves and that you can't, like, avoid it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can certainly misinterpret it with your view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means they don't even have a mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because their views deny the basic mundane aspects of their experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what it means there is mother, there is father.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mother is mother.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no lower threshold than that in your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people might talk about it on some occasion, but fundamentally, their view would be like an external assumption of a scientific world, for example, which says, well, in reality, we are just, you know, lumps of flesh.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing's real.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why everything is constantly impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's nothing to do with Buddhist teaching whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is mother, there is father.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your threshold.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the impermanence you discern within that, it's that impermanence of ownership, impermanence of appropriation, impossibility to kind of be a controlled master of things, because they were risen on their own.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you realize, ah, it's the impermanence of my sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not impermanence of a random stone, tree, table, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how many times, I bet you heard yourself, people say that, yeah, modern science is proving that the Buddha was correct, because everything is constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you hear that from very, very senior established monks in their talks and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize, yeah, you can be in ropes for the rest of your life, hundred years, and still not even have a mundane right view, let alone supplementary.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's no one else's fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are always solely responsible for the views you hold.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recognition of
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, of things arising on their own, to what extent they arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognition of things as phenomena, if you want to call it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not jump into material explanation, not mystify it in the ideological explanation, but literally just know.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the experience of having a mother.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the experience of having a father.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the experience of doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the experience of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Already withdraw from that material content of it, that we are all so focused on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is the necessary basis for really discerning the signs of your mind as phenomena.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having these views prevents you from seeing your mind as a thing that has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is an absolute prerequisite for the right view, as the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Citta, nimitta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without it, you can't have the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you see your mind as an enduring thing, when obviously enduring things you deny with your own view?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need the mundane right view to get used to it and then to start seeing things that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind, feeling, intentions, on the level of enduring things.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why many people struggle with those three characteristics that the Buddha describes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arising is manifest, ceasing is manifest, resisting while changing is manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: People read that, but they always keep saying and keep holding the view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arising is manifest, persisting while changing is manifest, ceasing is manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they change the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because for them, it's all seen in the third person of me observing something lasting and then disappearing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arising is manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ceasing is manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: Persisting while changing is manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's already something that's not linear in the way people are used to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if linear observance is required for you to understand impermanence, all you need to do is wait for your body to die.
[SPEAKER_00]: Death will be the enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cessation is another arising, another manifestation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for people, cessation means the impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what the Buddha said millions of times.
[SPEAKER_00]: Arising is manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ceasing is manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, thing endures, and that enduring is also manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Resisting while remaining the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it relates to this, like, there is mother...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: A certain threshold that you don't overly, kind of, eh... overly determine with your interpretation of science and medicine, but you don't go the other way and then mystify it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then say everything is constantly whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you recognize there is the arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, there is the experience of cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, things are enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either in the form of arising or ceasing, they're enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's manifested as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we are basically caught in this manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is... You can't step outside of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem is you assuming the external point of view to it, which ultimately is what attavāda is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assuming the external self to this whole thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you basically can't step outside of manifestation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what defines wrong view as a wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: A view that contradicts the fundamental universal aspect of your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha did not invent the right view, did not invent the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: He just discerned it on the right terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, for that you need instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't accidentally arrive at it, because everything points in the wrong direction.
[SPEAKER_02]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_02]: Mundane right view recognizes the the the basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is an experience as a starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, like, you have there is an experience of emotionally charged experience of your father getting sick or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is the base.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you see, even most people's practice is about covering that up, denying it, removing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it bothers me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, my practice becomes management of what bothers me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you manage it through the wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: You manage it through saying
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, fundamentally, it's just a collection of atoms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what... that's another way of saying, fundamentally, there is no father.
[SPEAKER_00]: In reality, there is no father.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just my attachment that the father is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your father is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you start thinking like that, then your practice of dhamma cannot be the management.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can only result in uprooting of the problem in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your practice is secondary, means it's management, which means it's not the dhamma, even if you do the dhamma on account of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now you have no leeway of denying the fatherhood.
[SPEAKER_00]: The experience of there is a father.
[SPEAKER_00]: The experience of there is a mother.
[SPEAKER_00]: The experience there is an experience of doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I don't know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are the reason factually enduring present states of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you stop denying it, then you realize the only way to not be bothered by it, is to uproot the craving towards the feeling, as in remove the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not through saying, everything is already impermanent, thus I shouldn't suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, it's just a collection of flesh organs and constantly moving electrons, there is no father.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through denying it, you try to find a way out of what bothers you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's management of the fact that you're bothered in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you do dhamma rightly, you can't be bothered in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, there is no reason for you to deny your father, mother, divine realms, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why would you?
[SPEAKER_00]: The only reason people deny it is because they don't know other way of... other way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And Bhante, what about this experience of kama and vipāka?
[SPEAKER_01]: We don't have this experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, see, that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha never said, like, you must figure it...
[SPEAKER_00]: He actually said, thinking about karma vipāka will result in distraction or madness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's what you recognize.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know to what extent my actions will bear fruit.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your fact... that's your factual experience right there and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how would you act then?
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not dismissing karma, or if you don't have, like, a perfectly cut kind of template of how karma works, you realize, oh, crap, I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I better be really, really careful, because even when I think I might be doing good, I don't know for myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not worth the risk.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's same when people ask him about the next life, and the Buddha said, well, the truth is you don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your starting point.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you reflect.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I better act in the best-case scenario, in the worst-case scenario, just in case that it is true.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be too much to handle.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'll assume there is, because it will make me act carefully.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, win-win.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, win-win situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, it's basically a win-win situation, because you are preparing the ground for a rising of this...
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...super mundane right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because without that mundane, you cannot... No, the only reason people don't have the even mundane right view, is because they haven't taken up responsibility for their own existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, as I said, you can be a perfectly restrained monk for 60 years and still have not taken responsibility for your existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now you have tradition doing the responsibility for you, vinaya doing the responsibility for you, form doing the responsibility for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Look, you must take it on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You must do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which initially is going to result, oh, so I could then decide to not do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, a whim of thought can uproot your whole existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's very, very scary.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you just move from one authority, placing you into the next authority.
[SPEAKER_00]: Until, eventually, you go into the authority of old age, senile experience of, like, you know, not being bothered by anything, because you can't remember half of the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you say, ah, old age is so graceful and peaceful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, you know, sexual desire doesn't bother you, because you just went completely dormant, and you can't even bother thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, good luck.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not uprooting anything at that stage, if you haven't uprooted things when they were obvious, when you could have developed transparency, you're not going to do it after hammering them down with, like, decades of habits of wrong views.
[SPEAKER_03]: What do you think is the balance between, like, you know, we can... we have to obviously face doubts, because we don't know certain things.
[SPEAKER_03]: What's the difference between, like, getting kind of, eh... strewn around by those doubts, and you kind of just start, eh... going the other way, versus using your doubt in a way that can be useful?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the difference is whether you are aware of the presently enduring nature of the doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you doubt the content of something, but you can't doubt the experience of doubt being present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the best way to withdraw yourself from any involvement with content of your experience is the doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's where sātras, being in nothingness, starts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, being becomes revealed when you put yourself in question.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start questioning your own existence, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's how you arrive at your own existence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through questioning it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like academically, genuinely.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am, but I could have not been.
[SPEAKER_00]: Immediately withdraws you from the entire content.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you understand the nature of that, means you have fully transcended any form of pull that content can exercise over you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can doubt this, you can doubt that, but you can't doubt the experience of the present.
[SPEAKER_00]: There isn't doubt in regard to this content.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: The best of the worst of the wrong views is that one, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I could have...
[SPEAKER_00]: I could have been... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It could have been...
[SPEAKER_00]: It could have not been for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will not be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally withdrawn from any content, any possibility of the content.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you will let go of that, that's ārahaṅca.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for that, you will need the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But still, it's a good thing, even with the wrong view, to develop it, because it already primes you very closely to the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You already are on the level of recognizing the universal aspect of the enduring experience, not being pulled by the content of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sometimes doubt will affect you more, doubt will affect you less, but you will know that you are more or less on the right tracks, if you remain aware of the present enduring doubt as a state of mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I've been trying to think about when things like all these kinds of states of doubt, frustration, despair, trying to think about things, like, it's a question of, but am I, am I, how bothered am I by it in the first place?
[SPEAKER_03]: And it's, your mind kind of tells you that, like, it's almost like you're obligated to be bothered.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, if you're not bothered, you're not doing the effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must, I must do something, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then it's like, what if not being bothered by this is the effort?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not dismissing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not denying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, there is no doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no mother.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no father.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, at the same time, you're recognizing, okay, it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's real to that extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, now, the choice is you need to give in to the craving towards the content or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, that's how you find that middle ground.
[SPEAKER_00]: Neither completely dismissing it, nor completely giving in to it and following it, sort of, off with course.
[SPEAKER_04]: Part of it's mundane right view, at the end of its passage.
[SPEAKER_04]: It says, there are those who have realized for themselves direct knowledge and declare this world and the other world.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, there are those who have realized, yeah, who know.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's mundane, like you.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you know that it's possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the extent, the extent of the possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, like possibility, even for most people, even their own thoughts would be regarded as something that's not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, you know, because they're used to substance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Their view, the level of being, the level of proliferated consciousness, is on the level of substance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when their thoughts are there in the background, it's usually, oh, that's not even real.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact that you can call it not real, means there is something that can be called not real, which means that thing is real.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your view of this is not real, or it's less real, it's a complete contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you completely undo that, you will recognize that possibilities are real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: And to that extent, you understood that extent of this world, of the next world, of the current world, of all the possible worlds.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, coming to the knowledge that, oh, it's possible.
[SPEAKER_04]: Someone says it's possible to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes, exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Completely.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that possibility is present in everyone's experience right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And always is, always was.
[SPEAKER_00]: And will be as well.
[SPEAKER_04]: I mean, what do you do?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh!
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is mother, there's father.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is the possibility of freedom.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is the possibility of the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is the possibility of arahantship.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, yeah, there's no... there's no possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Usually, almost automatically, that's what I said when you read the previous passage.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start denying this basic... basic manifestation of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start justifying it with your external views, you will automatically arrive at the view of there's nothing to be attained anyway, or nothing can be really attained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I heard monks, many different monks, different seniorities, whatever, just openly say those things on dhamma sīla.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no, don't worry about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's just, that's just more attachment.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing to be attained.
[SPEAKER_00]: The more you practice, the less you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, maybe your practice makes you more ignorant, but not what the Buddha was teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not what Ajahn Chah was teaching, for Christ's sake.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you read his verses, it's quite clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, don't take it for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Understand it, and then you'll know it, at least to that extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, take it further, if it's not sufficient.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, oh, okay, nothing can be trusted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, okay, I don't trust anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's my view now.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what pleases me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, uh, what sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, there's nothing to be attained anyway
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: Naturally, through denial of that, naturally, you're going to deny everything, and you're not even... you won't even feel responsible for not becoming a Sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: And do you think there is a connection, maybe, between the two?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's too hard to do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Let me dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't feel obliged to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, even the Ajahn Chah himself said, if you're not... if you don't have the right view within the first five years, you're wasting your time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, but no, there's nothing to be attained.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I follow Ajahn Chah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's nothing to be attained.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no Suddhāpati, nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I also follow the Buddha, and I'm a Buddhist monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: But again, there's nothing to be attained.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It comes down, mundane reality comes down to accepting that responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there is possibility of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh!
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's my possibility of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's possibility of my awakening.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm responsible for it then.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is a possibility to be free.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm perfectly free.
[SPEAKER_00]: To choose to not go that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that means I will be responsible for not getting the results of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the first thing that hit me when I started reading the suttas as a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: When the Buddha says, there is suffering, there is freedom from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Come and see for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I remember, because I couldn't even find anybody say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now I found somebody said it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I remember it was finally somebody said it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I felt it like, I don't have to follow it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now I know there is, but I could go the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But I immediately I felt like, okay, so if I choose to not become a monk and practice this, I am fully responsible for whatever happens to me for the rest of my life, even if it's not my fault in lay terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is the world, there is freedom from the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: You choose the world, means you choose everything else that might come on account of that world.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's based on that choice of you not renouncing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that...
[SPEAKER_00]: I couldn't ignore that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I could not ignore that fundamentally, then, I'm responsible even for complete things that are completely out of your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you chose to stay in the domain where things out of your control can happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Good or bad, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, recognizing that there is the enlightenment, there is my enlightenment, my possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how can somebody, without acknowledging that existence of possibilities,
[SPEAKER_00]: Without reverting to some explanatory third-person wrong view, how can then he take that on as his practice?
[SPEAKER_00]: He can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: His practice is going to have a magical connection to the result.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I'm devotional, I'm this, I'm doing that, I respect tradition, I meditate three hours a day, I watch my nostrils, I watch the soles of my feet, and then enlightenment will happen to me on account of these observances and duties that I do.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Enlightenment cannot happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only develop it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In order to develop it, you need to know what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And how can you know what it is, when you're even denying the basic possibility of it being, in the first place?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, mundane view is very important.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it's not to be confused... A lot of people would say that, like, it's not possible for me, in this lifetime.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's when you realize, like, unless you feel that it's your duty to become a sotāpanna, you will never do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a hard thing to do, and the only way to do it is through full acceptance of responsibility for not doing it, which would be more unpleasant than trying to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you do it.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's your duty to become... to be free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Aha.
[SPEAKER_04]: Not duty, responsibility.
[SPEAKER_04]: Your responsibility, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, it's your respons... your highest responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're not free from suffering, it's on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're free from suffering, it's also on you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have a choice.
[SPEAKER_04]: No complaints.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_04]: Layman.
Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's good that you said this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you stay in the realm of Mara, it's your responsibility, whatever happened to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, whatever kind of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you'd be surprised how much people don't want to hear that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, no, you can stay a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever happens to you, literally, it's your fault.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to blame somebody, you can only blame yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to blame somebody for enlightenment, you can only blame yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And many people don't even want to admit that, because it's too unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly... there are... there is my action, there are results of my action.
[SPEAKER_00]: I... oh, my responsibility, my results, to the extent of infinity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Who knows?
[SPEAKER_00]: That domain, it just goes.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have no idea which means it's not worth the risk then, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Some people say that I cannot become arahant in this lifetime because of my karma.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I know.
[SPEAKER_00]: People say that because they talk about karma factually.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would only work
[SPEAKER_00]: If you genuinely develop your mind to the extent of seeing your past actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if I ask you, if I come and slap you in the face, because yesterday you came and you stole my, I don't know, my property.
[SPEAKER_00]: You, you say, okay, well, I deserved it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you have a memory of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you've done something 10 years ago, and somebody reminds you of it, you still say, okay, yeah, I've done that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now people try to sort of use kamma as an excuse for not doing anything, not having memory of it as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I don't remember what I've done, but I choose that lack of memory to be my excuse for not doing something now that I'm fully aware of I can do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm saying it wouldn't work even if you were to have a memory of it, let alone when you don't have a memory of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if that's your kamma from before,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the same karma from yesterday.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, what you've done yesterday is your karma.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you've done ten years ago is your karma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why stop then?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, maybe there are things that I've done ten lifetimes ago, and they will be as much as mine, as what I've done yesterday is mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't be anyone else's.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you choose to draw this invisible line, where your memory is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I don't remember.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not my problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't actually go the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't remember.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it's a big problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, things I don't remember in this life, that I can, you know, end up paying price or somebody reminds me of, are a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Imagine things that you don't remember from previous lives.
[SPEAKER_00]: How much of a problem they will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of using the lack of memory for kind of not feeling responsible, it should be the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lack of memory should make you responsible for everything, even if you have no memory of what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's very unpleasant for the mind that wants to deny it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not giving up the view of denying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you would feel responsible for something you've done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, today I do this because ten years ago I started, like, I don't know, developing certain habit.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't deny responsibility for it, because you still have a memory of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you deny responsibility because, yeah, maybe you can't practice properly because of your previous karma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your previous karma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your previous action.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you yourself are responsible for you yourself not being able to practice today.
[SPEAKER_00]: That responsibility, whether it's from 10 years ago, 10 lifetimes ago, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's yours, as much as always will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I can't become an arahant because of my previous karma means I can't become an arahant because I can't become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the reason in itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that is, yeah, that is the reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: But by kind of creating the loop of all khandhā memory, you kind of obscure your responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and I think it's probably also connected with what you said before, with these observances.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The person is following some kind of observances, some kind of practice without results.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, this kind of results, so then, he would end up with this kind of excuse, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because he was maybe meditating, he's been meditating 20, 30 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they would end up, they would end up with an excuse that reveals, relieves them of responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not the excuse of, wait a minute, maybe I've been doing it wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: I couldn't have been doing it wrong, because that would mean my efforts were wasted, but that's too unpleasant to admit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead, I'll just dismiss it.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just say, well, no, I'm doing everything
[SPEAKER_00]: But I can't get to it because of something in the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have no memory of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, something have no memory of it, means it doesn't exist for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, that which doesn't exist for you, you have no knowledge of, no memory, no perception of it, you use as a presently perceived reason for your failure.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you see how wrong that is, on a deeply rooted self-deceptive act of self-deception.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's really interesting what you are saying, because just recently I heard about one well-known teacher who would openly admit his kutujana,
[SPEAKER_01]: And he can't, in this life, because of this previous kamma, achieve anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he is a well-known teacher and he can teach others, still, to practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, here I am...
[SPEAKER_01]: They can, by his advices, because they are not bothered by that bad kamma he has.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because his advice is obviously on the level of mechanical instruction, that anybody can do or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's... if you have a view that that's what dhamma practice is, then, yeah, anybody can be the teacher.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not what a dhamma is, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, as we explained, the mundane view requires you to take on responsibility, which is not... cannot be done mechanically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can do... go through the same motions as I do, but your attitude is attitude of not accepting responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I can give you verbatim instruction, it won't work, because your attitude doesn't work, which means there's no dhamma there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you going through these motions is going through the literal motions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without a dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what Sīla Bhāgavatam Master means.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean rituals and rites and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, things that are obviously ridiculous, when it comes to practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means virtue, sīla, and duty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense of duty.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's my duty to sit cross-legged and meditate as a monk.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but why you do it?
[SPEAKER_00]: To what extent does it help you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you understand why you're doing it?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm just doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's my duty to do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And my virtue is also my duty.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a factor.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you abandon that fetter without abandoning your virtue, without abandoning your efforts?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what differentiates it.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, if it's a duty, means you bypass responsibility at least a little bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, I'm a judge.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's my duty to pass a judgment onto you.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in, I'm not responsible for sending you to jail.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, well, you chose to be the judge, which is the one who sends people to jail.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you introduce the proxy to cover up the fact that you are the one condemning people to die or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, but it's my duty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, because I need a job.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you need a job?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because I have a family.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why do you have a family?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you had sex with your wife.
[SPEAKER_00]: Was that also your duty?
[SPEAKER_00]: It wasn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you've done things you wanted to do and now you're refusing to accept responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, because you have six children.
[SPEAKER_00]: Generally, it would be your duty if somebody forced those children on you and you had to look out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even then, it wouldn't be your duty.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would be responsible or rather you would be free to accept it or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that scary bit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally, no matter which way your life went, what you invested in it, one morning you can wake up and decide to just... and leave all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: And having that, that edge present all the time, freaks people out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the mind is undeveloped, the mind is unrestrained, the mind has no basis of virtue and self-control.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just a sight of the edge makes the mind run in terror.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's probably the most, like, scary, scary thing to accept your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the most scary thing for monks when they are dead.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, like, my duty, my duty, my virtue, I must do this, vinaya, vinaya, and get extremely neurotic.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whereby, it's not even vinaya anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just some obscure, ridiculous interpretation upon interpretation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the rule is clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Context is clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything is clear.
[SPEAKER_00]: But a person can't sleep for five days just because mind is like, oh, what if, what if, what if.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because through avoiding responsibility, you actually make things worse for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can overwhelm you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And whenever, whenever circumstances present themselves in their way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, it's going to be much more unpleasant to accept responsibility for your virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, no, I am choosing to do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am choosing... it will then enable you to draw a line as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will not think that, because I know exactly what's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even those people know exactly what's right.
[SPEAKER_00]: But because they're projected in this third-person view of duty, something that must be done, that's nothing to do with me, then they also keep needing the third person's confirmation and affirmation of what they're doing to be right.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the doubt can only be settled by going around and asking people, and so they tell you what you want to hear,
[SPEAKER_00]: By reading, reading, reinterpreting, interpreting, interpreting, until you get what you want to hear, by having everybody else does the same rites and rituals you do, because if they don't, it will question the validity of the stuff you do, everything is out there, nothing is in me, nothing is my responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why those people would generally be upset, existentially threatened, if you wear your sabong differently.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, here we wear flip-flops, he doesn't wear flip-flops, mind already panic, because there is there is a different way about this, which means it's not a duty then, the way I took it to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, in this tradition, we wear our robe like this, and we put our cups down like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, well, I'm part of this tradition, and I put my cup like this.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Meltdown.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because their practice is out there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, this is what must be done, which means this is what must be done by everyone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if they don't do it, then I realize I'm responsible for keep assuming that this is what must be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it brings you back onto that personal responsibility that you wanted to avoid in the first place, which is why you latched onto that factor of duty and virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is no dhamma without sīla, but dhamma is not a sīla.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as regards the sīla, but the paramāsa, can we say...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I understand, it's basically about this attitude.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you change that attitude, you remove just paramāsa, but the sīla remains the same, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, yeah, sotāpanna doesn't abandon his sīla to become a sotāpanna, as in, he starts doing the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, outwardly, you maybe don't...
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't see any difference in behavior of that person.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that person who is fully projected in that external third-person view, they can't see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: For them, saying dhamma is not sīla means, so I must not keep sīla then.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you say that sīla, bhāta-paramāsa, is a factor of you assuming this is my duty and virtue by doing so, avoid personal responsibility for it, for them that means, okay, so I should disrobe and go and, you know, find a wife and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean that at all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sīla remains unchanged, but your attitude is now changed.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not you doing it anymore on account of the external assumed authority or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're doing it because you see it exactly as a necessary basis for discerning the nature of phenomena of your mind, feelings and intentions, which you now understood is the way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, unless that responsibility is taken on for doing it in the first place, even the wrong things you're doing, even the fetters you're holding, you can't uproot them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you deny that is a fetter, you cannot undo that fetter, because you're not seeing it.
[SPEAKER_04]: What would be another translation of that sīla pāṭṭhā?
[SPEAKER_00]: I think virtue and duty is a good translation.
[SPEAKER_04]: The non-responsibility in virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, yeah, sure, sure, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Forecasting of your responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, virtue and duty as a basis of you avoiding responsibility for virtue and duty.
[SPEAKER_01]: But sīla can be also like a behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, that's the one meaning of behavior, sīla.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, behavior, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can have also vichā, sīla.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And maybe also we can say, like, that with cikicā, it can be also about responsibility, that you are basically casting off your responsibility for right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, fundamentally, yeah, all of the hindrances partake in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same centrality, your will.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now came actually a question.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we have that third fetter, uh, sakāyāditi.
[SPEAKER_01]: But seems that basically craving and this craving, hate and... yeah, that craving is still present even in that person with... Yeah, sakāyāditi is on that level of... it's an utter vāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the level of their view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what, what frees you?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is that freedom of breaking through this?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, knowing, like, for understanding what, what your āthavāda is, frees you from āthavāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can still have craving for these five aggregates?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, but to what extent?
[SPEAKER_00]: You will only know when you're free from āthavāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: Putujana can't get accurate representation of what craving is present in sotāpanna without becoming a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's important thing to keep in mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people's minds are used to having it all laid out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this is what arahant is.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what sotāpādā is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, and I'm... No.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you truly understand what it is, you'll be at least a sotāpādā here.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that must... that criteria must not be compromised, because you'll end up... otherwise, you'll end up thinking you understood what arahant is without being one, which means there is no understanding of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order to understand ātavāda, you need to... in order to free yourself from ātavāda, you
[SPEAKER_00]: And vadādvāda is what I described it to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even like, like even commentaries, because Pali, it's clear what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's assuming an external, like, so to speak, assuming the self, sense of self externally, as in, so you can describe to yourself, based my experience as a whole, call it five aggregates, call it whatever you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: If something is external to it, how could I even think of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: How could I think of something external to my thinking?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a complete contradiction in turn.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, if you start looking at your vague sense of self that you have, ambiguous, it kind of has that property.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's completely independent of everything that's happening to it, which means it's not independent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you keep maintaining that utter blatant discrepancy, because you never think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even you go to practice dhamma, become a monk, and that takes you even further away from thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just find a niche of things you do now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't do everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're restrained, but you're still doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you're doing your meditation technique, and you're doing your methods, and you're doing this, and you're doing this, and you're doing this, and your responsibilities, and you never stop and think about contradictions that you carry throughout all that doing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you can't do your way out of enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do your way out of ignorance towards enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't, like, keep performing kamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will then, directly, they will free you from kamma while you're performing the kamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only
[SPEAKER_00]: The right karma, so to speak, the right action of renunciation, saying no to the senses, you know, becoming a monk and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, there is some karma involved, some acts, on the basis of which you can understand the nature of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, you need to abandon evil by establishing the basis of good, so that you can then understand both and free yourself utterly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sīla Bhāgavatam is on the level of you still assuming the connection between you doing things and contributing towards enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only efforts to understand nature of things contribute to enlightenment, but you'll only know how much in hindsight.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't tell at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only once you get the right view, you realize, oh, yeah, it's all those nights I spend like thinking and pondering relentlessly on the meaning of my feelings or intentions, nature of consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a direct way that results in understanding of those very things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not until you understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the simile of the axe, the handle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, after all, now I need to replace it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I've done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Look, I used it all up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: Worn out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance is gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people, well, they have difficulty accepting that, because it makes things much more overwhelming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because first, you accept responsibility for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You accept responsibility for not being a sotāpanna, which is also equally unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the whole confusion also, what do I do then?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it's hard to give up the view of... well, more like hard to give up the dependence on having something to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have nothing to do,
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, you get crushed with that nothing to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I must do something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what I was saying to you this morning, wasn't I?
[SPEAKER_00]: On the way back from Pune.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, like for many monks, worldly doing gets replaced with what monks do.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's equally the same principle, the same thing, the same existential attitude.
[SPEAKER_00]: I do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I don't do anything, I'm going to start sinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's so difficult to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even when those people try to do nothing, the attitude will try to make it into something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, me doing nothing now, becomes your forceful doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you need some external thing which would, like, confirm that you are not just a loser, but you are doing something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, yeah, measure... well, no, like, yeah, okay, you know, maybe I don't have the right view, but I've been practicing for 15 years, so surely... no, no, I refuse to admit, accept that that might be... might have been for waste, like, wasteful.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, it surely comes to something.
[SPEAKER_00]: But maybe it was not wasted.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe... Yeah, but how would you know that?
[SPEAKER_00]: ...a little bit more and... Yeah, a little bit more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, 15 years now, a little bit more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're honest to yourself, you realize, well, would I know how a little bit more help me?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I'm just hoping for magic to happen after the next step, to win the lottery, to get the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the same level, magical thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know how what I've been doing relates to getting the right understanding, because all I've been doing is doing of different kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: I went to this teacher who told me to do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I went to another teacher who told me to do this.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, I was doing this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm doing everything now.
[SPEAKER_00]: I got my own way of doing things, all on the level of depending on something to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, yeah, the more you invest in it, more effort invested, the harder it will be for you to look at it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: I still don't know what I'm doing and I still depend on having something to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Especially if you spent like thousands of hours in meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's terrible to admit that it was just a waste of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I think it becomes impossible to admit.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like full-on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Admitting would equal breakdown.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I want to ask another thing about this sakāyāditya, because basically, as I understand it, that atta is included in your experience, and your experience is basically conditioned, is external, as you say, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it cannot be independent atta.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's not, but it's not like...
[SPEAKER_00]: The reason why what you just said is not accurate is because even when you have a thought of what externally conditions your experience, that cannot be that external because of which your experience is conditioned.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you experience that which is beyond your experience, unless you experience it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're experiencing it, it cannot be external to your experience, because it's your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean external to the sense of me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any notion of external, it's internal for you already.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how you are put out of other.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not leaving, not giving it any way out.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you are always actually in... Well, you have no choice, of course, but your view doesn't think that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any form of allowing, any form of external, it's allowing the basis for the for the ātavāda to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, see, even when you say, my ātavāda is conditioned by external, you already assumed external, independent of your experience, and that's the basis for your very ātavāda you're trying to undo.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, I got it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, can you always, like, try to catch this this kind of point?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep bringing the point back to your mind, and then not losing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point that, no matter what sense of self you yourself might be, lofty, far, internal, external, it's all within the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you think it's all within, it's not external, that thought of that external is already within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you stop providing basis for it, because it needs constant nutriment.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remove the basis, then the nature of it will become apparent after a period of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just repeat, basically, the same kind of process to, like, to catch this... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's gonna happen is, you start repeating it, it's gonna all make sense in the beginning, but then you start doubting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you will have to find a way of getting back to it through that doubt.
[SPEAKER_00]: And keep... because each time you start doubting, it means you're reaching to a new level of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, a new idea, you're so inspired, everything makes sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've been doing it, then that inspiration runs away, and then you just start doubting it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you have to keep pushing forward.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the whole point is, yeah, develop the theme,
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't provide the basis for any notion of external in regard to your experience of the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like there is no external.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is external, which is experienced by you, which means that external is fundamentally internal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Very good.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, I realized one thing that you cannot make any kind, like a progress, if you try to catch these pañca khandhas, these five aggregates, as that external.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the fact that you keep assuming that you could, means you keep allowing possibility of external.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that in itself is already wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, I was like watching, trying to watch these pañcakandhas, you know, like that matter and other things that they are, maybe impermanent, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can't move further, because you are always like watching something... Well, your watching of pañcakandha is within pañcakandha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, assuming, like, assuming any form of out of it is the basis for rātavāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't, like, I will stop rātavāda, but what I can do is stop maintaining this obvious contradiction of assuming external through these little unquestioned attitudes and habits and thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You undo that to the sufficient, like, extent necessary, there will be no room for rātavāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you realize, yeah, there is a self.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's another thing when people say there's no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uh-huh.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, there is self.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that thing which is self is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is that thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's pañca khandhā.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people don't even arrive at it, because their whole practice... there is no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is the external view of my aggregates already, modern science, what not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, I just extend it even further with another layer of wrong view, saying there is no self.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just deny your denial even further.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, all of it is assumed external to you, which means you're through and through atavāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first, you need to admit it, that there is that sense of self, and then stop putting it external to the experience as a whole, but see it within it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Change the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all you need to do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, discover new things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just keep, eh... sorry, cease perverting them, perverting the order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cease messing them up.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a person who understood, would understand the Buddha for the first time, would say, oh, it's like putting the second first and the first second.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Tathāgata cleared it out.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like what was upside down, now it's proper.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can take it in a poetic sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can take it in a very literal sense, which is exactly what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: The world, it's actually sense within the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable to be outside.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, anybody can... Oh, yeah, I get that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I get that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, great.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, develop that theme day and night.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't abandon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter what you're going through in your life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't abandon the theme that your sense of self can never be external in regard to your thought of external as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: I see.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you will be sort of literally sucking out the oxygen that's necessary for that sense of self to keep enduring in that external manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no basis for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It cannot be maintained.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, there's nothing mystical about it, but there is nothing scientific about it either, because science is already the wrong view.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to have instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, this is what I need to look for.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you need to start discerning it in your own experience, because if I tell you this, and now you go as a... and make a mantra out of it, and just mechanically repeat things that I told you, you're not going to do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, it's not incidental that all these people, they misquote Ajahn Chah, are also people who praise Buddha, Buddha meditation, where you're just repeating Buddha, rhythmically, and that results in samādhi.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it's quite... Good luck with that samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's quite amazing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't figure out how you came to these conclusions by yourself, you know, just reading suttas, because I'm also reading them, but I can't see these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I've never been avoiding my responsibility from the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's where what you read in the suttas start to apply much more accurately.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's less pleasant, but that's not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no other way like you can do by avoiding this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can suffer to different accounts on account of it, but it's the same thing that needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: And people who suffer on different accounts, people who like, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: If you have been developed, sort of, like, have proper samādhi, proper virtue, then you suffer less, on account of the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: If your starting point, even as a layman, is right there, without sufficient proper samādhi, or sufficient proper virtue, you will suffer much more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But nevertheless, either way, the point is to arrive at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, yeah, you can read all you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, for goodness sake, I mean, people get into nirnaveda and completely misquote it and misrepresent it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not out of malice, out of complete misunderstanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: No idea what he's talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: He had a dedicated life to the teaching in the Veda.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you hear the views, and it's quite shocking how they're able to maintain such contradiction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he could not have been more blunt and more clear in many other ways.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even that won't make any difference if there is not even a mundane acceptance of responsibility and transparency in regard to your own intentions and actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that doesn't mean just, yes, I'm responsible.
[SPEAKER_00]: That means that, no, I must feel this.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must feel this existential anxiety on account of responsibility for things that I don't even have a memory of.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's a very unpleasant state to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you start accepting it, then you realize practice of dhamma, at first, is not optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: Secondly, it's not up to anyone else or any external pattern, form, method, institution.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's upon me being free from craving or not free from craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's also how you realize that practice of dhamma doesn't manage your suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: It uproots it altogether.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't suffer in the first place, thus there's nothing to manage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you're free from any burden, any duty, anything you must do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: No reason to do anything anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you won't arrive to that through blindly adhering to the dependence on needing something to do, which prevents you from admitting that you're responsible for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I don't hold to fixed views.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your fixed view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You must not trust anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you shouldn't trust even that statement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does Sotāpanna have suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: From Arahant's point of view, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: From Bhutujana's point of view, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Knowing the way out of suffering means you can't suffer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what Sotāpanna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: He knows the way out of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if putujana doesn't accept, doesn't take that as a criteria, he will then think that he knows what sotāpanna is, to what extent, while still being a putujana.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way to know sotāpanna is to become one, as you already said.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what is that suffering which, from the point of Arahant, is in sotāpanna?
[SPEAKER_00]: Symptoms of the illness that are left while illness has been cured.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, nuisance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nuisance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, nuisance.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say you're dying of cancer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, your joints ache, your lymph nodes are swollen, everything hurts, everything is unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: But really, you mentally suffer and you're dying of cancer.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now, I come and I cure your cancer.
[SPEAKER_00]: But your joints still hurt.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still don't have hair.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still... your lymph nodes are still swollen.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you know you're free from cancer.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'd be quite joyous, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: You wouldn't mind any of this discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, from the point of view of somebody who is free from even those residual symptoms, yeah, you can say there is some sort of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: But not from the point of view of somebody who is still in sheer terror of dying of cancer.
[SPEAKER_00]: He's not even bothered by his symptoms.
[SPEAKER_00]: His only bother is the fact that he's dying of cancer.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you approve that, then symptoms won't bother you even more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Symptoms will bother you even less.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why sotāpanna can turn away and sort of go back and whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or lay people can be sotāpannas and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Still live the life and be attracted to sensuality and everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you have uprooted the illness completely and you fully understand that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like, oh, what is happening to me?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you know exactly what's happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no amount of symptoms can reintroduce the illness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that gives tremendous confidence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of which, you can become careless and complacent, because you don't care.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ultimately, you know that you cannot become ill.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't matter what you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he still doesn't have a full understanding of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he has full understanding, but he has not dwelt enough in the theme of full understanding, not long enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, I just gave you the how to uproot ātavāda.
[SPEAKER_00]: You must... you can't just think about the theme once or twice.
[SPEAKER_00]: You must keep discerning it and dwell in it for as long as it takes, until the handle of the axe wears out.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't know when it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: For Sauribhāna, it's even clearer than that, because he knows exactly what to think and what themes to develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: He just needs to do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha keeps encouraging causing arising sense of urgency.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because for most putuginas, when they think sotāpanna, it's pretty much almost an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, it's basically almost like what I am, a putugin.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can't see sotāpanna for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, they're not a sotāpanna.